<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<unit unitid="Y_504_1172">
   <uan>Y/504/1172</uan>
   <unitnumber>1</unitnumber>
   <title>Patterns of Child Development</title>
   <description><![CDATA[
<p>Every child is special and unique, but each of us learns to do things according to the same pattern. What’s your earliest memory? Can you remember how old you were when you learnt to swim? Were there some things you found easy to achieve and some that took a bit longer to learn, for example, riding a bicycle or writing your name? Understanding child development may help you to answer these questions and it will also explain why, as individuals, we develop skills and knowledge at different rates.</p>

      <p>This unit aims to develop your knowledge and understanding of child development. You will learn about five different areas of development – physical, cognitive, communication and language, emotional and social – and how these areas are linked.</p>

      <p>In each of these five areas there are expected patterns of development based on the norms for different ages. These developmental norms are sometimes referred to as milestones. They are useful for several reasons. Early years professionals and health professionals monitor children’s progress in achieving these milestones. While it is usual for children to have different rates of progress, it is important for professionals to know when children are showing unusual progress or patterns in their development. This sometimes means that a child needs additional support.</p>

      <p>Knowing the expected patterns of development and associated milestones for 
each area of development also helps adults to anticipate the next stage of a child’s development in each area. You will investigate how adults in early years settings can support children’s development.</p>

      <p>As part of your course, you will learn about the expected patterns of development, and if you choose to work with children this will help you plan activities and understand why children are doing certain things.</p>

      <p>In this unit you will:</p>
]]></description>
   <glh>
      <glhvalue>30</glhvalue>
   </glh>
   <level>1 and 2</level>
   <assessmentmode id="">External</assessmentmode>
   <learningobjective loid="Y_504_1172.LOA">
      <title>A</title>
      <learningobjectivetext>Understand growth and development in children</learningobjectivetext>
   </learningobjective>
   <learningobjective loid="Y_504_1172.LOB">
      <title>B</title>
      <learningobjectivetext>Understand the characteristics of children’s development from birth up to eight years</learningobjectivetext>
   </learningobjective>
   <learningobjective loid="Y_504_1172.LOC">
      <title>C</title>
      <learningobjectivetext>Understand how adults in early years settings can support children’s development</learningobjectivetext>
   </learningobjective>
   <unitcontent>
      <unitsection sid="Y_504_1172.LOA">
         <title>Learning aim A: Understand growth and development in children</title>
         <sectiontext><![CDATA[<p>
               <b>Topic A.1 Growth and development</b>
            </p>
            <p>
               <b>Growth</b>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>Key aspects of children’s growth are changes to physical size, the skeleton, muscles and the brain.</li>
               <li>Children’s height, weight and head circumference are measured to monitor growth, ensuring it is consistent with expected patterns, and to highlight potential issues at an early stage.</li>
               <li>Children’s growth is plotted on centile charts.</li>
               <li>Growth is determined by heredity, hormones, nutrition, sleep, illness and emotional influences.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>Development</b>
            </p>
            <p>Child development is defined as the increasing acquisition of skills and knowledge gained by a child.</p>
            <ul>
               <li>Development should be viewed holistically as children acquire skills at varying rates in different areas of development.</li>
               <li>Developmental norms are sometimes called milestones. They have been determined by looking at the data of thousands of children and considering the average or ‘typical’ milestones. Using these norms or milestones helps to understand the patterns of development.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>Development</b>
            </p>
            <p>can be broken down into five key areas</p>
            <ul>
               <li>Gross motor and fine motor physical development is to do with movement; gross or large movement of limbs, developing locomotion, balance and coordination, and fine manipulative movement of fingers developing hand–eye coordination.</li>
               <li>Cognitive development is the way children develop thought processes, perception, memory, imagination and problem solving, and are able to increase their knowledge and understanding of their environment.</li>
               <li>Communication and language development is the way children communicate and develop speech, including reading and writing.</li>
               <li>Emotional and behavioural development is how children develop feelings and express their emotions through behaviour, and includes the development of self-concept and self-esteem.</li>
               <li>Social development includes how children develop friendships with peers, cooperate with others and become aware of role models.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>continued</b>
            </p>]]></sectiontext>
      </unitsection>
      <unitsection sid="Y_504_1172.LOB">
         <title>Learning aim B: Understand the characteristics of children’s development from birth up to eight years</title>
         <sectiontext><![CDATA[<p>
               <b>Topic B.1 Characteristics of children’s development</b>
            </p>
            <p>Learners must be aware that children can develop at varying rates in different areas of development. They must know the usual sequence and the characteristics of each child development milestone from birth up to eight years.</p>
            <ul>
               <li>Knowledge of the usual sequence in physical (gross and fine motor skills), cognitive, communication and language, emotional and social development.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>Birth up to twelve months Gross motor development:</b>
            </p>
            <p>Newborns are born with reflexes – sucking, rooting, startling, grasping – which help them survive. Movements are uncontrolled and uncoordinated:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>at three months able to lift up head and chest when on their stomachs and bring hands together over body</li>
               <li>at six months can roll over from back to front</li>
               <li>at nine months can sit unsupported and is usually mobile by crawling or rolling, may pull up to stand alone and walk by holding on to furniture</li>
               <li>at twelve months pulls up to stand, stands alone, walks holding on to furniture.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>Fine motor development:</b>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>no coordinated movement but newborns will grasp things put into their hands as a 
reflex action</li>
               <li>at three months can watch their hands and hold a rattle for a moment</li>
               <li>at six months can reach for a toy and move a toy from one hand to the other</li>
               <li>at nine months can use a pincer grasp (index finger and thumb) to grasp objects, 
can deliberately release objects by dropping them</li>
               <li>at twelve months can use pincer grasp to pick up small objects, points using 
index finger.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>Cognitive development:</b>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>at one month ‘freezes’ if hears a sound played softly</li>
               <li>at three months can recognise familiar routines, is alert and follows movement with 
eyes if objects are close</li>
               <li>at six months can explore objects by putting in mouth, recognises voices</li>
               <li>at eight or nine months can look for dropped objects and objects that they see 
being hidden</li>
               <li>at twelve months enjoys throwing toys to the ground and watching their descent, learns by trying things out and repeating if successful. This approach to learning is called ‘trial by error’.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>Communication and language development:</b>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>at one month can turn head to adult voice, at six weeks begins to coo</li>
               <li>at three months smiles when hears a familiar voice</li>
               <li>at six months makes short babbling sounds, such as ‘da’ and ‘ba’</li>
               <li>at nine months understands ‘no’, vocalises in long strings of babbling</li>
               <li>at twelve months knows own name and understands simple instructions.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>continue</b>
            </p>
            <p>d</p>]]></sectiontext>
      </unitsection>
      <unitsection sid="Y_504_1172.LOC">
         <title>Learning aim C: Understand how adults in early years settings can support children’s development </title>
         <sectiontext><![CDATA[<p>
               <b>Topic C.1 Understand how adults in early years settings can support children’s development</b>
            </p>
            <p>Learners will be expected to understand that children’s development can be positively influenced by adults in early years settings and that the lack of adult support may lead to delays in development. Learners must be able to recognise why some forms of adult support are age/stage appropriate and be expected to suggest appropriate age/stage support.</p>
            <p>
               <b>Gross motor and fine motor physical development:</b>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>meeting children’s physical needs by providing a well-ventilated and relaxing sleep area for children to sleep at regular intervals</li>
               <li>meeting diet and nutritional needs in accordance with policy and parental wishes</li>
               <li>providing opportunities to be outdoors</li>
               <li>providing age-appropriate resources and activities that encourage gross and fine motor skills both indoors and outdoors</li>
               <li>providing resources and activities that encourage children to touch, feel and explore objects with their senses</li>
               <li>providing opportunities for children to meet their physical needs.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>Cognitive development:</b>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>providing objects and games that encourage children to develop their memory and imaginative skills, and helping them to think about others</li>
               <li>providing age- and stage-appropriate activities and resources that encourage problem-solving skills</li>
               <li>providing opportunities for children to visit different places and experience 
new things</li>
               <li>encouraging children to ask questions, helping children to link new experiences to past ones (memory and recall).</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>Communication and language development:</b>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>taking time to talk, and smiling and maintaining eye contact to encourage 
listening skills</li>
               <li>encouraging speaking and listening skills by using nursery rhymes, picture books, telling stories, reciting rhymes, ‘show and tell’, and by asking questions such as ‘what’, ‘where’ and ‘who’ to encourage speaking</li>
               <li>providing role-play activities for pretend play</li>
               <li>encouraging writing skills by copying their own name and familiar names and words</li>
               <li>encouraging creative expression through stories, poetry, dance, drama and 
making music.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <b>continued</b>
            </p>]]></sectiontext>
      </unitsection>
   </unitcontent>
   <printdocument>Y_504_1172</printdocument>
</unit>
