<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification>
<unit>
<uan>H/504/1174</uan>
<t>Unit 3: 	The Principles of Early Years Practice</t>
<te>Level:</te><l>1 and 2</l>
<te>Unit type:</te><ty>Mandatory</ty>
<te>Guided learning hours:</te><glh>60</glh>
<te>Assessment type:</te><at>Internal</at>
<i_t>Unit introduction</i_t>
<i_te>There are some general principles that underpin work in early years settings. These principles shape the way settings are run and the ways in which adults in settings work with children and their families.</i_te>
<i_te>In this unit you will look at some of the key principles that are reflected in best practice in early years. You will learn about inclusive practice as a way of valuing children and ensuring that they can benefit from the opportunities within the setting. You will also explore how children are empowered to ensure that children learn to become independent and develop a strong self-image, as well as ways in which this is put into practice.</i_te>
<i_te>A further principle of working with children is the key person approach, which early years settings use to meet children&#8217;s emotional and care needs. In this unit, you 
will learn why the key person approach is important to children&#8217;s learning and development. If you wish to work in early years, it is important that you have a 
good understanding of the principles as you will need to incorporate them into 
your practice.</i_te>
<la_t>Learning aims</la_t>
<la_te>In this unit you will:</la_te>
<ol type="la_al1">
<li>understand the importance of inclusive practice in early years</li>
<li>explore ways in which early years settings implement inclusive practice</li>
<li>understand how children are empowered in early years settings</li>
<li>understand the importance of the key person approach in supporting children&#8217;s development.</li>
</ol>
<la_st>
Learning aims and unit content</la_st>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h1>What needs to be learnt</la_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h2>Learning aim A: Understand the importance of inclusive practice in early years</la_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_te_s>Topic A.1 How children benefit from inclusive practice</la_te_s><la_te>Inclusive practice is the way in which children and their families are valued and support is given regardless of age, disability, race, background, gender or lifestyle in order that children and their families can benefit from the services and opportunities available. Learners must understand how children benefit from inclusive practice.</la_te><la_te_s>The positive effects of inclusive practice on children&#8217;s outcomes, including:</la_te_s><ul type="la_bl1"><li>development of a positive self-image affecting confidence, motivation and positive attitudes towards others</li>
<li>developmental benefits as any needs are identified and a wide range of opportunities is available and, if necessary, adapted to meet needs</li>
<li>opportunities to play and socialise with other children and thus gain social skills and learn to express feelings and emotions</li>
<li>development of self-efficacy, a &#8216;can do&#8217; attitude, that gives children confidence to try out new activities or cope in unfamiliar situations</li>
<li>emotional wellbeing as a result of being accepted and cared about by others</li>
<li>positive benefits to health outcomes as physical needs are met through 
inclusive practice</li>
<li>development of enduring positive attitudes towards others as a result of observing how to value and support others regardless of their age, disability, race, background, gender or lifestyle.</li></ul><la_te_s>Topic A.2 How non-inclusive practice may affect children&#8217;s outcomes</la_te_s><la_te>Learners must understand how children may be affected by non-inclusive practice.</la_te><la_te_s>How outcomes for children may be affected by non-inclusive practice:</la_te_s><ul type="la_bl1"><li>poor self-image as a result of feeling unwanted, helpless or inferior</li>
<li>low self-efficacy as children may have &#8216;learnt helplessness&#8217; or see themselves 
as victims</li>
<li>delayed development as a result of late identification of needs or needs not being met</li>
<li>poor health outcomes if physical care needs have not been attended to, e.g. individual dietary needs unmet</li>
<li>educational outcomes lower as a result of not being given the same opportunities to develop skills and knowledge because needs were not met.</li></ul>
</td>
</tr>
</table>


<table>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h1>What needs to be learnt</la_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h2>Learning aim B: Explore ways in which early years settings implement inclusive practice</la_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_te_s>Topic B.1 Ways in which early years settings implement inclusive practice</la_te_s><la_te>Learners must understand how early years settings ensure that children and their families are respected and valued and how children&#8217;s unique needs can be met, allowing all children to be included and supported.</la_te><la_te_s>Inclusive practice in early years settings, including:</la_te_s><ul type="la_bl1"><li>adopting a non-judgemental attitude, e.g. respecting individual differences, 
cultures and beliefs, uniqueness of each child</li>
<li>implementing a welcoming environment, e.g. posters in different languages, 
greeting parents</li>
<li>using or displaying resources that reflect children&#8217;s lives and celebrate diversity, 
e.g. home corner, dressing-up clothes</li>
<li>developing strong relationships with children and their families to ensure that children&#8217;s individual needs are fully understood</li>
<li>adapting provision to meet the individual needs of children</li>
<li>keeping children safe</li>
<li>establishing routines</li>
<li>adults consistently acting as positive role models.</li></ul>
</td>
</tr>
</table>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h1>What needs to be learnt</la_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h2>Learning aim C: Understand how children are empowered in early years settings</la_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_te_s>Topic C.1 The importance of empowerment of children in early years settings</la_te_s><la_te>Learners must understand reasons why early years settings seek to empower children and how empowerment contributes to children&#8217;s learning and development.
Definition of empowerment: giving children involvement in decisions that affect them, appropriate to their age and level of understanding.
Why early years settings seek to empower children:</la_te><ul type="la_bl1"><li>children have a right to be informed, involved and consulted about all decisions that affect them</li>
<li>to value children as their feelings and opinions are taken into account</li>
<li>to show respect to children</li>
<li>to help children to respect themselves and others</li>
<li>to involve children in decision making, e.g. play opportunities, routines.</li></ul><la_te>How empowerment benefits children, including:</la_te><ul type="la_bl1"><li>benefits to physical development, e.g. children gain confidence to try new challenges, more motivated to practise skills, helps children to make decisions about risk</li>
<li>benefits to emotional development e.g. self-esteem encouraged from being given opportunities to be involved in decision-making processes, more likely to be able to manage own behaviour if they have had some input in decisions about appropriate behaviour, boundaries and expectations</li>
<li>benefits to social development, e.g. children develop self-respect and learn to respect and value others and the feelings of others</li>
<li>benefits to cognitive development, e.g. involvement in decision-making process encourages motivation, perseverance and concentration.</li></ul><la_te_s>Topic C.2 How adults in early years settings empower children</la_te_s><la_te>Learners must understand how adults in early years settings empower children, and the importance of ensuring children are empowered in ways appropriate to their age/stage of development.
Ways adults in early years settings empower children appropriate to their age/stage of development, including:</la_te><ul type="la_bl1"><li>involving children in physical care routines and encouraging them to be involved in self-care to support independence, e.g. washing, dressing</li>
<li>giving children appropriate control and privacy when dressing, e.g. half closing a door so that toddlers can use the toilet in private</li>
<li>encouraging children to help themselves at meal and snack times</li>
<li>supporting child-initiated play whereby children can make choices as to what and how they play, and with whom</li>
<li>involving children in planning so that children feed back what they have enjoyed doing and can make suggestions as to what they wish to do next</li>
<li>involving children in all aspects of preparing the environment, e.g. choosing equipment to put out, tidying away, preparing snacks.</li></ul>
</td>
</tr>
</table>


<table>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h1>What needs to be learnt</la_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h2>Learning aim D: Understand the importance of the key person approach in supporting children&#8217;s development</la_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_te_s>Topic D.1 Why the key person approach is used in early years settings</la_te_s><la_te>Learners need to understand that the key person approach is the way in which early years settings meet children&#8217;s emotional and care needs through the development of a strong and consistent relationship with a child and their family.</la_te><ul type="la_bl1"><li>Definition of key person role as someone who develops a strong and consistent relationship with a child and their family to ensure emotional and care needs are met.</li>
<li>Main roles of key person, e.g. developing a special bond with the child, sharing information with parents, supporting transition and observing the child.</li>
<li>Key person approach is a requirement of early years education/care frameworks, 
e.g. Early Years Foundation Stage (England), Foundation Phase (Wales).</li>
<li>Key person approach helps parents to effectively exchange and share information effectively to support children&#8217;s physical care and development, e.g. dietary needs, allergies, health conditions, ensuring medical and physical needs are met.</li></ul><la_te_s>Topic D.2 How the key person approach supports children&#8217;s development</la_te_s><la_te>Learners must understand how the key person approach, in meeting children&#8217;s emotional needs, enables children&#8217;s development to be supported.
How the key person approach supports children&#8217;s development:</la_te><ul type="la_bl1"><li>emotional development is supported as young children are prevented from becoming distressed when separated from parent/carer, e.g. key person understands children&#8217;s individual emotional needs and ways to comfort them, children feel more secure</li>
<li>language development is supported, e.g. children communicate more to people with whom they have a strong relationship, key person knows how best to communicate with child</li>
<li>children&#8217;s learning is supported, e.g. key person knows children&#8217;s interests, children feel more confident to try new experiences and explore</li>
<li>children&#8217;s physical development is supported, e.g. key person is aware of the child&#8217;s stage of development, recognises suitable equipment and resources</li>
<li>children&#8217;s social development is supported as children learn to make relationships beyond their family circle, e.g. key person approach helps children to develop relationships with others in the setting.</li></ul>
</td>
</tr>
</table>



<ac_t>Assessment criteria</ac_t>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_h1>Level 1</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Level 2 Pass</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Level 2 Merit</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Level 2 Distinction </ac_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">
<ac_h2>Learning aim A: Understand the importance of inclusive practice in early years</ac_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>1A.1</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Outline three benefits 
to children of inclusive practice in early years settings.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>2A.P1</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Describe how children benefit from inclusive practice in early years settings.
#</ac_te>
</td>
<td rowspan="2">
<ac_te_e>2A.M1</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Explain the potential impact on children 
of inclusive and non-inclusive practice in early years settings, using appropriate examples.
#</ac_te>
</td>
<td rowspan="2">
<ac_te_e>2A.D1</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Compare how inclusive and non-inclusive practice affects children in early years settings, using case studies.
#</ac_te>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>1A.2</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Outline three ways in which children may be affected by non-inclusive practice in early years settings.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>2A.P2</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Describe ways in which children may be affected by non-inclusive practice in early years settings.
#</ac_te>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">
<ac_h2>Learning aim B: Explore ways in which early years settings implement inclusive practice</ac_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>1B.3</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Outline how inclusive practice is implemented in selected early years settings.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>2B.P3</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Describe how inclusive practice is implemented in selected early years settings.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>2B.M2</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Explain how inclusive practice is implemented in a selected early years setting. </ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>2B.D2</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Assess the extent to which inclusive practice is successfully implemented in a selected early years setting.</ac_te>
</td>
</tr>
</table>


<table>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_h1>Level 1</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Level 2 Pass</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Level 2 Merit</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Level 2 Distinction </ac_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">
<ac_h2>Learning aim C: Understand how children are empowered in early years settings</ac_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>1C.4</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Outline why adults in early years settings seek to empower children.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>2C.P4</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Explain why adults in early years settings seek to empower children.</ac_te>
</td>
<td rowspan="2">
<ac_te_e>2C.M3</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Explain how effective empowerment of children can benefit their development, using appropriate examples.</ac_te>
</td>
<td rowspan="2">
<ac_te_e>2C.D3</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Assess the extent to which an early years setting is successful in empowering children, using a case study.</ac_te>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>1C.5</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Identify how adults in early years settings can empower children.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>2C.P5</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Describe how adults in early years settings can empower children.</ac_te>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">
<ac_h2>Learning aim D: Understand the importance of the key person approach in supporting children&#8217;s development</ac_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>1D.6</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Identify two reasons why the key person approach is used in early years settings.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>2D.P6</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Explain why the key person approach is used in early years settings.</ac_te>
</td>
<td rowspan="2">
<ac_te_e>2D.M4</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Explain how the key person approach supports children&#8217;s development, using appropriate examples.</ac_te>
</td>
<td rowspan="2">
<ac_te_e>2D.D4</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Evaluate the contribution of the key person approach to a selected child&#8217;s development.</ac_te>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>1D.7</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Identify ways that children&#8217;s development 
is supported by the key person approach.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>2D.P7</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Describe how the key person approach supports all areas of children&#8217;s development.</ac_te>
</td>
</tr>
</table>



<tg_t>Teacher guidance</tg_t>
<tg_h1>Resources</tg_h1>
<tg_te>There are no special resources needed for this unit.</tg_te>
<tg_h1>Assessment guidance</tg_h1>
<tg_te>This unit is assessed internally by the centre and externally verified by Edexcel. Please read this guidance in conjunction with </tg_te><tg_te_e>Section 8 Internal assessment</tg_te_e><tg_te>.</tg_te>
<tg_te>When learners undertake assessments, they need to be aware that assessment criteria are hierarchical. For example, within a learning aim, the Level 2 Merit and Distinction criteria directly build on and encompass the expected learning of the Level 2 Pass criteria. Where there are examples of comparison, review, analysis, discussion 
or in-depth evaluation of selected examples, these must build on the breadth of understanding required through the definition of topics in the content section.</tg_te>
<tg_te>This unit can be achieved either through one holistic assignment designed to 
assess all assessment criteria within a level, or by several, smaller assignments. 
For example, the assignment can be set within a specific early years setting and 
explore how the principles of early years practice are applied within that setting.</tg_te>
<tg_h1>Learning aim A</tg_h1>
<tg_te_s>For 2A.P1: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners must describe how children benefit from inclusive practice in early years settings. They are expected to give examples of ways in which children may benefit from inclusive practice in early years settings. These could include examples that illustrate advantages to children&#8217;s development, wellbeing and health, using the unit content in topic A.1. Learners&#8217; descriptions are expected to show understanding of the concept of inclusive practice.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2A.P2: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners must describe ways in which children may be affected by non-inclusive practice in early years settings. Learners could use examples that describe ways children may be affected if settings do not apply inclusive practice. For example, if a child is excluded from joining in a physical play opportunity with others as equipment is not suitable for their needs, they may feel inferior, resulting in a poor self-image. Learners should be able to describe at least three different ways in which children may be affected.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2A.M1: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners are asked to explain the potential impact on children of inclusive and non-inclusive practice in early years settings. Learners must use appropriate examples to explain the ways in which children&#8217;s health, development and wellbeing and may be affected by inclusive and non-inclusive practice in early years settings, linking the unit content in topic A.1 and topic A.2. The examples or case studies must demonstrate accepted best inclusive practice and examples of non-inclusive practice in early years settings.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2A.D1: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners must compare how inclusive and non-inclusive practice affects children in early years settings, using case studies. Learners are expected to extend their piece of work to contrast both the long- and short-term outcomes to children&#8217;s health, development and wellbeing of inclusive and non-inclusive practice in early years settings.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 1A.1: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners are expected to outline three benefits to children of inclusive practice in early years settings.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 1A.2: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners must outline three ways in which children may be affected by non-inclusive practice in early years settings.</tg_te>
<tg_h1>
Learning aim B</tg_h1>
<tg_te_s>For 2B.P3: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners must describe how inclusive practice is implemented in selected early years settings. Learners could use examples from settings for children of different ages to describe approaches used by the settings to demonstrate inclusive practice. Learners are expected to explore the unit content for topic B.1 and show understanding of the concept of inclusive practice in meeting children&#8217;s unique needs.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2B.M2: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners need to explain how inclusive practice is implemented in a selected early years setting. They could use examples of approaches, which may be case studies. Learners need to explain the approaches used by the setting to support inclusive practice &#8211; for example, how providing a florescent ball enables a child with visual impairment to play a ball game with other children shows that a setting has provision to meet individual needs and has included and supported the child.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2B.D2: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners need to assess the extent to which inclusive practice is successfully implemented in a selected early years setting. They are expected to extend their piece of work to make judgements about how successful the approaches used were in ensuring that children and their families were respected and valued, 
in meeting children&#8217;s unique needs and in allowing all children to be included and supported. This could include suggestions for different approaches the settings 
could use.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 1B.3: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners need to outline how inclusive practice is implemented in selected early years settings. Three different ways should be given.</tg_te>
<tg_h1>Learning aim C</tg_h1>
<tg_te_s>For 2C.P4: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners need to explain why adults in early years settings seek to empower children. Learners could use examples to support their explanation, which must include why settings seek to empower children and how children benefit from being empowered. Learners are expected to explore the content given for topic C.1 and show understanding of the concept of empowerment.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2C.P5: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners are expected to describe how adults in early years settings 
can empower children. They could use examples that show how adults empower children using the content given for topic C.2 &#8211; for example, how a snack time in a setting for children aged three years up to five years is organised by the adults to enable the children to prepare the food for snack, set the table, choose when they have their snack and offer choices of food. Learners could then describe how this supports empowerment by involving children, supporting decision making, encouraging choices and supporting independence and self-care. Learners are expected to use examples from settings for children of different ages.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2C.M3: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners need to explain how effective empowerment of children can benefit their development. They could use a case study to provide appropriate examples. Learners should be encouraged to link the unit content of topic C.2 to explain how the setting empowers children in ways appropriate to their age/stage 
of development.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2C.D3: </tg_te_s><tg_te>The teacher will select an appropriate early years setting that will give learners the opportunity to study this topic in depth. Learners are expected to make a judgement about how successful the setting has been in empowering children and why their approaches have been successful in ensuring children are involved in decisions that affect them.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 1C.4: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners need to outline why adults in early years settings seek to empower children.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 1C.5: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners must identify how adults in early years settings can empower children, citing three different ways.</tg_te>

<tg_h1>Learning aim D</tg_h1>
<tg_te_s>For 2D.P6: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners must explain why the key person approach is used in early years settings. They could use examples from settings for children of different ages to support their explanations, using the content given for topic D.1. For example, the key person approach in a setting for children for two up to five years gives emotional support to children starting school as children may be anxious in this transition. Learners are expected to show understanding of how the key person approach in settings provides for the emotional and care needs of children aged from birth up to eight years through the development of a strong and consistent relationship with a child and their family.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2D.P7: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners are to describe how the key person approach supports all 
areas of children&#8217;s development. Learners&#8217; descriptions must cover all areas of development (physical, cognitive, communication and language, social and emotional development, and social development). Examples of ways in which development may be supported are given in topic D.2.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2D.M4: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners need to explain how the key person approach supports children&#8217;s learning and development. Learners need to use appropriate examples which could be case studies of children in different settings across the age ranges (birth up to two years, two years up to five years, five years up to eight years). Learners must use the examples to explain how having a key person approach in place helps to meet the emotional and care needs of the children, and how their development is supported, with reference to the unit content in topic D.1 and 
topic D.2.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 2D.D4: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners are to evaluate the contribution of key person approach to a child&#8217;s development. Learners need to use a case study and make a judgement about the value of the key person approach to all areas of the child&#8217;s development. This could consider the impact on the child&#8216;s development if the key person approach 
had not been effective in meeting the child&#8217;s emotional and care needs.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 1D.6: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners need to identify two reasons why the key person approach is used in early years settings.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>For 1D.7: </tg_te_s><tg_te>learners must identify ways that children&#8217;s development is supported by the key person approach and include different areas of development.</tg_te>


<sao_t>Suggested assignment outlines</sao_t>
<sao_te>The table below shows a programme of suggested assignment outlines that cover the assessment criteria. This is guidance and it is recommended that centres either write their own assignments or adapt any assignments we provide to meet local needs and resources.</sao_te>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<sao_h1>Criteria covered</sao_h1>
</td>
<td>
<sao_h1>Assignment</sao_h1>
</td>
<td>
<sao_h1>Scenario</sao_h1>
</td>
<td>
<sao_h1>Assessment evidence</sao_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<sao_te>1A.1, 1A.2, 2A.P1, 2A.P2, 2A.M1, 2A.D1</sao_te>
</td>
<td>
<sao_te>Why inclusive practice is important in early years settings</sao_te>
</td>
<td>
<sao_te>As part of your preparation for work, the manager of the setting has asked you to look 
at inclusive practice. This will help you to understand why early years settings place great importance on ensuring all children and their families are valued and supported. You are to produce a report.
You need to:</sao_te><ul type="sao_bl1"><li>describe how children benefit from inclusive practice in early years settings</li>
<li>describe how children may be affected by non-inclusive practice in a setting</li>
<li>use appropriate examples to explain the potential impact on children of inclusive and non-inclusive practice in early years settings</li>
<li>compare how inclusive and non-inclusive practice affects children in early years settings, using case studies.</li></ul>
</td>
<td>
<sao_te>The report could be written or IT-produced. </sao_te>
</td>
</tr>
</table>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
<sao_h1>Criteria covered</sao_h1>
</td>
<td>
<sao_h1>Assignment</sao_h1>
</td>
<td>
<sao_h1>Scenario</sao_h1>
</td>
<td>
<sao_h1>Assessment evidence</sao_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<sao_te>1B.3, 2B.P3, 2B.M2, 2B.D2</sao_te>
</td>
<td>
<sao_te>How early years settings implement inclusive practice</sao_te>
</td>
<td>
<sao_te>The manager was impressed with your understanding of the importance of inclusive practice and has asked you to contribute to the handbook for students to help them to understand how the setting enables all children to be included and supported. You are to produce a chapter for the work experience book for early years students.
You need to:</sao_te><ul type="sao_bl1"><li>describe how inclusive practice is implemented in selected early years settings</li>
<li>explain how a selected early years setting implements inclusive early years practice</li>
<li>assess the extent to which inclusive practice is successfully implemented in a selected early years setting.</li></ul>
</td>
<td>
<sao_te>The handbook could be written/IT-produced accounts.</sao_te>
</td>
</tr>
</table>



<table>
<tr>
<td>
<sao_h1>Criteria covered</sao_h1>
</td>
<td>
<sao_h1>Assignment</sao_h1>
</td>
<td>
<sao_h1>Scenario</sao_h1>
</td>
<td>
<sao_h1>Assessment evidence</sao_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<sao_te>1C.4, 1C.5, 2C.P4, 2C.P5, 2C.M3, 2C.D3</sao_te>
</td>
<td>
<sao_te>How children are empowered in early years settings</sao_te>
</td>
<td>
<sao_te>Part of the induction process for new staff 
in the early years setting includes providing information about empowering children and how the adults in the setting work to involve children in decisions that affect them. Your manager has asked you to produce materials for induction. The setting provides for children from birth up 
to eight years so your information needs to be relevant for staff working with children across the whole age range. You are to produce a handout for new staff.
You need to:</sao_te><ul type="sao_bl1"><li>explain why adults in early years settings seek to empower children</li>
<li>describe how adults in early years settings can empower children</li>
<li>use appropriate examples to explain how adults in an early years setting empower children</li>
<li>assess the extent to which an early years setting is successful in empowering children.</li></ul>
</td>
<td>
<sao_te>The handout could include written/IT-produced accounts.</sao_te>
</td>
</tr>
</table>


</unit>
</specification>

