<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification>
<unit>
<uan>H/504/0719</uan>
<t>Unit 28:	An Introduction to Work as a Community Nursery Nurse</t>
<te>Level: </te><l>3</l>
<te>Unit type: </te><ty>Optional specialist</ty>
<te>Guided learning hours: </te><glh>60</glh>
<te>Assessment type: </te><at>Internal</at>
<i_t>Unit introduction</i_t>
<i_te>Did you know that Community Nursery Nurses work closely under the supervision of health visitors to improve the health and wellbeing of families with children under 8? Health promotion involves preventing ill health and early detection of health difficulties. Promoting children&#8217;s health includes immunisation and developmental screening programmes. It also involves advising and supporting parents to prevent accidents in the home and provide a healthy diet for their children.</i_te>
<i_te>The knowledge and skills you have developed about work with young children complement the work of the health visiting service. Health visitors have a primary role in promoting child health and Community Nursery Nurses support the work of the health visiting team in this.</i_te>
<i_te>In this unit you will learn about the roles and responsibilities of Community Nursery Nurses. You will learn about child health promotion and the skills required by Community Nursery Nurses to be effective in promoting child health by encouraging participation through the development of trusting, respectful relationships with families.</i_te>
<la_t>Learning aims</la_t>
<la_te>In this unit you will:</la_te>
<ol type="la_al1">
<li>understand the roles and responsibilities of a Community Nursery Nurse</li>
<li>understand the range and scope of child health promotion in the community</li>
<li>understand the skills needed to work as a Community Nursery Nurse.</li>
</ol>

<la_st>Learning aims and unit content</la_st>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h1>Unit content</la_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h2>Learning aim A: Understand the roles and responsibilities of a Community Nursery Nurse</la_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ul type="la_bl1"><li>The role of a Community Nursery Nurse (CNN), including services aimed at improving the health and wellbeing of families with children up to the age of 8.</li>
<li>The range of work as a CNN, to include undertaking child development assessments, health promotion, child protection and work with individual families and parenting groups, encouraging play, promoting positive behaviour and giving advice on infant feeding and nutrition, hygiene and safety and accident prevention in the home.</li>
<li>The context for work as a CNN, including child health clinics and visiting families in their own homes.</li>
<li>How the CNN works as part of a skill-mix team to promote child health, including health visitors, CNNs, qualified nurses and administrative support workers.</li>
<li>The importance of understanding the roles and responsibilities of other members of the team in relation to the health of children and families, to ensure effective partnership working in order to make sure clients get the best service.</li>
<li>Why it is important to understand that the CNN is accountable to the Nursing and Midwifery Council registrant or delegating professional, and only undertakes activities which are delegated.</li>
<li>The importance of following agreed policies and procedures for confidentiality, complete and accurate record keeping and lines of reporting, to ensure consistency of care for the child and the child&#8217;s carer.</li></ul>
</td>
</tr>
</table>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h1>Unit content</la_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h2>Learning aim B: Understand the range and scope of child health promotion in the community</la_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ul type="la_bl1"><li>That health promotion is a process to enable people to increase control over, and to improve, their health.</li>
<li>The principle that health promotion is not something that is done on or to people, but is done by, with and for people, either as individuals or as groups.</li>
<li>That primary prevention involves the prevention of diseases and conditions before their onset, including making the environment safe, maintaining a safe water and food supply, and immunising against infectious diseases.</li>
<li>That secondary prevention involves measures for early detection of departures from good health and for prompt and effective corrective actions.</li>
<li>Factors that affect child health, including pre- and post-natal factors, biological factors, environmental factors and emotional factors.</li>
<li>The current immunisation programme for children and young people.</li>
<li>The importance of immunisation programmes in preventing infections and how information about these may be given to parents, including in child health records, in leaflets and verbally.</li>
<li>The role of health surveillance programmes in promoting child health, including growth monitoring, and physical and developmental screening.</li>
<li>Current advice given to parents about feeding and nutrition programmes which follow national recommendations, including those for breastfeeding, weaning and healthy eating.</li>
<li>The advice given to parents to reduce accidents in the home, including safety precautions in relation to developmental stages and safety equipment.</li>
<li>The advice and support given to parents to reduce the risk of sudden infant death syndrome, including preventing overheating, placing babies on their back with their feet touching the end of the cot and risks when babies are exposed to cigarette smoke.</li>
<li>How adult health and lifestyle issues impact on the health of children, to include smoking, postnatal depression, disability, substance misuse and domestic violence.</li>
<li>How child health is promoted in work with families, to include parenting programmes, support groups for mothers with postnatal depression and smoking cessation support.</li></ul>
</td>
</tr>
</table>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h1>Unit content</la_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<la_h2>Learning aim C: Understand the skills needed to work as a Community Nursery Nurse</la_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ul type="la_bl1"><li>The importance of developing trusting, respectful relationships with families when offering help and guidance for effective child health promotion.</li>
<li>The skills needed to promote health, to include involving people and encouraging participation, understanding, being supportive and non-judgemental, excellent communication and negotiation skills, caring and empathising.</li>
<li>The importance of reflecting the culture, attitudes and values of an individual and the community in which they live in health promotion, to ensure help and advice given is sensitive and appropriate for individuals.</li>
<li>Why it is important to be well informed and accurate when giving information to promote child health, as families need accurate, current information to make informed decisions and inaccurate information leads to loss of trust.</li>
<li>When to refer directly to health professionals, including child protection concerns.</li>
<li>How to signpost to services, including having accurate information about available services, providing information in appropriate formats for families to access.</li></ul>
</td>
</tr>
</table>

<ac_t>Assessment criteria</ac_t>
<ac_te>The criteria are applied to learner evidence to determine attainment. Refer to the assessment guidance for the evidence requirements.</ac_te>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_h1>Pass</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Merit</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Distinction </ac_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<ac_h2>Learning aim A: Understand the roles and responsibilities of a Community Nursery Nurse</ac_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>3A.P1</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Describe the work of a Community Nursery Nurse.</ac_te><ac_te_e>3A.P2</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Explain the responsibilities of a Community Nursery Nurse as a member of a skill-mix team.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>3A.M1</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Analyse the scope of the Community Nursery Nurse role as a member of a skill-mix team.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<ac_h2>Learning aim B: Understand the range and scope of child health promotion in the community</ac_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>3B.P3</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Describe factors which affect the health of children.</ac_te><ac_te_e>3B.P4</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Explain how child health is promoted through:</ac_te><ul type="ac_bl1"><li>immunisation programmes</li>
<li>physical and developmental screening programmes. #</li></ul><ac_te_e>3B.P5</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Explain, using examples, how the Community Nursery Nurse works with parents to prevent accidents to children in the home.</ac_te><ac_te_e>3B.P6</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Describe ways in which the Community Nursery Nurse promotes child health through supporting parents with adult health and lifestyle issues.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>3B.M2</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Discuss, using examples, the range of responsibilities of the Community Nursery Nurse in immunisation and developmental screening programmes.</ac_te><ac_te_e>3B.M3</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Analyse how health promotion programmes support child health.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>3B.D1	</ac_te_e><ac_te>Evaluate, giving examples, the effectiveness of the contribution of the Community Nursery Nurse to child health promotion.</ac_te>
</td>
</tr>
</table>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_h1>Pass</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Merit</ac_h1>
</td>
<td>
<ac_h1>Distinction </ac_h1>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">
<ac_h2>Learning aim C: Understand the skills needed to work as a Community Nursery Nurse</ac_h2>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<ac_te_e>3C.P7</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Review the importance of communication skills for effective child health promotion.
3C.P8	Explain, using examples, why accuracy of information is important in child health promotion.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>3C.M4</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Analyse the importance of maintaining a professional approach in supporting children and families.</ac_te>
</td>
<td>
<ac_te_e>3C.D2</ac_te_e><ac_te>	Assess the challenges that face the Community Nursery Nurse when working with children and families in health promotion.</ac_te>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
<ac_te># English Functional Skills signposting</ac_te>
<ac_te>* Mathematics Functional Skills signposting</ac_te>
<ac_te>&#167; Information and Communication Technology Functional Skills signposting</ac_te>

<tg_t>Teacher guidance</tg_t>
<tg_st>Assessment guidance</tg_st>
<tg_te>Proposed assessment structure for the unit:</tg_te>
<ul type="tg_bl1">
<li>Assignment 1: 3A.P1, 3A.P2 and 3A.M1.</li>
<li>Assignment 2: 3B.P3, 3B.P4, 3B.P5, 3B.P6, 3B.M2, 3B.M3 and 3B.D1.</li>
<li>Assignment 3: 3C.P7, 3C.P8, 3C.M4 and 3C.D2.</li>
</ul>
<tg_te_s>Assignment 1</tg_te_s>
<tg_te>Learners could prepare information about the roles and responsibilities of a Community Nursery Nurse to be included in a careers advice pack for early years learners for the assessment of learning aim A.</tg_te>
<tg_te>To achieve 3A.P1, learners could use case studies to describe the work of a Community Nursery Nurse. Reference needs to be made to the role, range and context of the work as given in the unit content.</tg_te>
<tg_te>For 3A.P2, learners could use examples to explain the responsibilities of a Community Nursery Nurse as a member of a skill-mix team, to include members of the team, accountability, lines of reporting and confidentiality.</tg_te>
<tg_te>To achieve 3A.M1, learners could use the case studies used for 3A.P1 to assess the effectiveness of the Community Nursery Nurse as a member of a skill-mix team, with reference to the responsibilities explained for 3A.P2.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>Assignment 2</tg_te_s>
<tg_te>Learners could produce guidance for induction of Community Nursery Nurses for this assignment for 3B.P3, 3B.P4, 3B.P5, 3B.P6, 3B.M2, 3B.M3 and 3B.D1.</tg_te>
<tg_te>To achieve 3B.P3, learners could use case studies to describe factors which affect the health of children. Reference to the unit content, for example prenatal and postnatal factors, must be included.</tg_te>
<tg_te>For 3B.P4, learners could refer to National Health websites and information provided by health visitors at baby clinics and General Practice surgeries to explain how child health is promoted through immunisation programmes and physical and developmental screening programmes. The current immunisation programme, growth monitoring and physical and developmental screening programme must be included and the difference between primary and secondary prevention explained.</tg_te>
<tg_te>To achieve 3B.M2, learners could build on 3B.P4 and use case studies as examples to discuss the effectiveness of the Community Nursery Nurse in immunisation and developmental screening programmes, including their role in informing parents. </tg_te>
<tg_te>To achieve 3B.P5, learners could use case studies as examples to explain how the Community Nursery Nurse works with parents to prevent accidents to children in the home, with reference to advice about preventing sudden infant death syndrome, safety precautions in relation to developmental stages and appropriate equipment.</tg_te>
<tg_te>For 3B.P6, learners could use case studies to describe ways in which the Community Nursery Nurse promotes child health through supporting parents with adult health and lifestyle issues. Reference to the unit content, for example support groups for mothers with postnatal depression, must be included.</tg_te>
<tg_te>To achieve 3B.M3, learners could use case studies to analyse how health promotion programmes support child health, with reference to immunisation and physical developmental screening programmes, working with parents to prevent accidents in the home, and supporting parents with adult health issues.</tg_te>

<tg_te>For 3B.D1, learners need to use examples and make reasoned judgements, based on evidence from further reading, to evaluate the effectiveness of the contribution of the Community Nursery Nurse to child health promotion. Reference needs to be made to all of the unit content of learning aim B.</tg_te>
<tg_te_s>Assignment 3</tg_te_s>
<tg_te>Learners could develop a presentation about the skills needed to work as a Community Nursery Nurse, as outlined in the unit content, to achieve 3C.P7. Copies of PowerPoint&#174; presentation notes printed on A4, or presentation slides/OHPs with development notes, should be submitted as evidence.</tg_te>
<tg_te>For 3C.P8, learners could use case studies as examples to explain why accuracy of information is important in child health promotion; reference to the unit content, for example enabling families to make informed decisions, must be included.</tg_te>
<tg_te>To achieve 3C.M4, learners could use case studies to analyse the importance of maintaining a professional approach in supporting children and families with reference to promoting child health.</tg_te>
<tg_te>For 3C.D2, learners could use case studies and further reading to make reasoned judgements to assess the challenges that face the Community Nursery Nurse when working with children and families, in relation to effective health promotion.</tg_te>
<tg_te>It is strongly recommended that learners, especially when engaged in extended writing, have opportunities to continue to develop their literacy skills. Where appropriate, learners should be given formative feedback on areas such as grammatical structure, spelling, punctuation and presentation. Some learners may also benefit from specific teaching on how to write in ways that show analysis and evaluation.</tg_te>
<tg_st>Resources</tg_st>
<tg_te>There are no special resources needed for this unit.</tg_te>
</unit>
</specification>

